{
  "sourceFile": "2020-2021-International-Geography-Bee-Finals-A-Set.txt",
  "count": 10,
  "items": [
    {
      "qno": 1,
      "question": "This country's New Georgia Islands contain the uninhabited rock known as Kennedy Island, where U.S. president John F. Kennedy was stranded during World War Two. Many World War II shipwrecks can be found in this country’s Ironbottom Sound, also known as The Slot. Control of Henderson Field was contested during a campaign on this country’s island of Guadalcanal. For the point, name this Melanesian nation with capital Honiara, which is named for a wealthy Biblical king.",
      "answer": "The Solomon Islands"
    },
    {
      "qno": 2,
      "question": "This river contains Kunta Kinteh Island, which was a former hub of the trans-Atlantic slave trade. This river, which rises in the Fouta Djallon [[FOO-tah jah-LOHN]] highlands, includes the city of Juffure [[joo-FOO-reh]] along its banks. This river discharges into the Atlantic at the city of Banjul. For the point, name this West African river which shares its name with a small country surrounded on three sides by Senegal.",
      "answer": "Gambia River"
    },
    {
      "qno": 3,
      "question": "This desert acts as a testing site for the NASA-funded Earth-Mars Cave Detection Program. The European Southern Observatory operates three major facilities in this desert, including Paranal [[pah-rah-NAHL]] Observatory, due to this desert's high elevation and historic lack of rainfall. Located between the Andes Mountains and the Chilean Coastal Range, this desert formed due to a rare two-sided rain shadow. For the point, name this desert in northern Chile, the driest in the world.",
      "answer": "Atacama Desert"
    },
    {
      "qno": 4,
      "question": "This city contains Chimelong Paradise, which is its country's largest amusement park. This city is home to the only completed opera house designed by Zaha Hadid. An outdated name for this city is still used to name its primary language, which has approximately 80 million speakers. This Pearl River Delta city was once known as the \"City of Rams.\" The capital of Guangdong Province, for the point, what is this city in southern mainland China which was formerly known in the west as Canton?",
      "answer": "Guangzhou"
    },
    {
      "qno": 5,
      "question": "One of these structures named for the Guarani people is located in southern Brazil and is composed of Piramboia Formation sandstones. The Great Artesian Basin in Australia is widely considered the largest one of these structures in the world. One of these structures in the Great Plains is called Ogallala. For the point, name these layers of permeable subsurface rock which act as reservoirs for fresh water.",
      "answer": "Aquifers 2020-21 V/JV Spring Geography Bee V/JV Spring Geography Bee - Finals"
    },
    {
      "qno": 6,
      "question": "The Gates of Alexander were legendarily built in this range. The unrecognized Republic of Artsakh in this range suffered a defeat in a 2020 war that saw heavy fighting in Nagorno-Karabakh. The Armenian Highlands lie south of this mountain range, whose highest point is Mt. Elbrus. For the point, name this mountain range that runs between the Black Sea and the Caspian Sea, which, along with the Urals, separates Europe from Asia.",
      "answer": "Caucasus"
    },
    {
      "qno": 7,
      "question": "This territory's most popular scuba tourist center is Stingray City. This territory's West Bay District is home to a notable turtle farm and conservation area, and this territory was originally named Las Tortugas in reference to its many turtles. This territory's capital of George Town lies near a tourist attraction named Seven Mile Beach. For the point, name this British Caribbean territory which is named for a small alligatorid.",
      "answer": "Cayman Islands"
    },
    {
      "qno": 8,
      "question": "One of these places is home to the Married Couple Rocks which are tied together by a sacred rope. The most sacred example of these places is rebuilt every twenty years and is dedicated to a sun goddess. In 927, the Engi-shiki listed nearly 3000 of these places and their kami. Entrances to these places are often marked by torii gates and shimenawa rice straw ropes. For the point, name these places of worship used by an indigenous Japanese religion.",
      "answer": "Shinto shrines"
    },
    {
      "qno": 9,
      "question": "This state's city of Appleton anchors the Fox River Valley and contains Lawrence University. This state’s Door County and its namesake Dells are popular tourist destinations. A city of 105,000 people in this state is home to the only community-held pro-football team in the USA. This state's suburban cities of Racine and Kenosha sit along Lake Michigan. This state is home to the smallest metro area to host a major league sports team, Green Bay. For the point, name this state which is home to Milwaukee and whose capital city is Madison.",
      "answer": "Wisconsin"
    },
    {
      "qno": 10,
      "question": "This river originates in the Gada Qu [[CHOO]] headwaters of Tibet. The Myitsone [[MYITS-hohng]] Dam was originally planned to be built along this river near the confluence of the Mali and N'mai rivers. The Mu [[MOO]] and Chindwin rivers are tributaries of this other river whose major port cities include Bhamo and Mandalay. This river discharges nto the Andaman Sea. For the point, name this chief river of Myanmar.",
      "answer": "Irrawaddy River"
    }
  ]
}